"The Efficacy, Safety, and Side Effects
of Botox and Facelifts"
Anti-aging medicine
is one of the fastest growing
medical specialties,
and often targeted at women,
who are urged to restore
their youthful appearance
by "any and all
available means."
This includes surgery.
92 percent
of cosmetic procedures
are performed on women,
most commonly Botox, fillers,
and laser or chemical
peel skin resurfacing,
but millions in the U.S. undergo
cosmetic surgery every year,
including hundreds of thousands
of face-lifts.
There's no consensus on
the best face-lift technique.
None have been shown to be
definitively better than others.
A systematic review found that
most of the studies
on the newest techniques
were mere case series,
one of the lowest levels
on the hierarchy of evidence,
basically composed of a string
of glorified anecdotes.
According to one of the largest
and most up-to-date analyses,
face-lifts are considered
relatively safe when performed
by a board-certified
plastic surgeon,
with surgical complications
only happening
in about 1 in 20 cases,
most often hematomas,
where blood collects
under the skin flaps,
or minor infections.
Serious infections,
like facial necrotizing
fasciitis
caused by flesh-eating bacteria
are rare,
as is pyoderma gangrenosum,
a disfiguring, skin ulcerating
autoimmune disease
that can be triggered
by face-lift surgery.
Other uncommon consequences
include scarring, hair loss,
and injuries
too gruesome to show.
Nerve injuries occur in at most
a few percent of cases,
but only about
1 in 1000 procedures
may result in permanent
facial nerve injury.
About two-thirds of face-lifts
are performed under
general anesthesia,
which is associated with
a greater risk of complications.
The most important way
to mediate risk
is to refrain from smoking.
Smoking can increase the risk
of skin flap necrosis,
or tissue death,
up to twenty-fold.
Patients should refrain from
smoking at least a month before
and month after surgery.
Tempering expectations
is also important.
Approximately 1 in 3 women
experience a period
of postoperative depression,
but this may just be
in reaction to
the temporary distortion
and discoloration
of swelling and bruising
after surgery.
The most profitable
cosmetic procedure is Botox,
in the billions,
as well as the most common,
performed more than four million
times a year in the US alone.
It all started when
a group of surgeons noticed
that patients with Bell's palsy,
facial paralysis,
didn't have as many wrinkles.
So what about
injecting minute amounts
of the nerve-blocking toxin
that causes botulism
to paralyze a few
facial muscles on purpose,
and a multibillion-dollar
industry was born.
The effect is temporary,
typically lasting
three to four months
until the body can grow back
new nerve terminals.
In response to cases of
respiratory failure and death
occurring hours or even weeks
after injection,
in 2009 the FDA mandated
a black box warning
regarding the potential
spread of the toxin
resulting in death
from swallowing
and breathing difficulties
occurring hours, days,
or weeks after injection.
However, most of these
complications were tied
not to cosmetic uses
but to treating muscle spasms--
for example in cerebral palsy.
For wrinkles, only 30 to 60
units of the toxin may be used,
compared to an average of about
180 for severe muscle spasms,
though still a far cry
from the estimated lethal dose
of perhaps 3,000 units.
The dose is given in MU,
"mouse units,"
with one MU being the amount
capable of poisoning
half of a group
of albino mice to death.
In studies, less than
1 in 2,000 Botox procedures
resulted in complications,
which can include droopy
eyelids, double vision,
an asymmetrical smile,
or the Spock,
a devilish curvature of
the outer portion of the brow.
Unfortunately, not all such
procedures are performed
under such
controlled conditions.
In many states,
there is surprisingly little
or no regulation
as to who can deliver Botox,
leading to a rapid increase
in injections
by nonmedical personnel.
In one five-ish year period,
about 30,000 complications
allegedly tied to Botox
were reported to the FDA,
most commonly pain, swelling,
and eyelid or eyebrow drooping,
but most adverse effects are
transient and self-limited.